Guide to the Fred Mallender Collection of British Commonwealth Postage Stamps
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
Fred Mallender Collection of British Commonwealth postage stamps
1937-1992
MSS 1
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
15
circa 40,000 stamps, in 108 albums and 6 boxes
Consists of about 40,000 postage stamps from countries or territories of the British Commonwealth, from 1937-1992, collected by Fred Mallender.
Mallender, Fred, 1930-2003
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series: I. Early Albums, 1937-1955; II. Albums, 1947-1992; III. Later Stamps, Unmounted, 1988-1992; IV. Gibbons Catalogues, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Fred Mallender II, Yale Class of 1952.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of about 40,000 postage stamps from countries or territories of the British Commonwealth, from 1937-1992, collected by Fred Mallender. All stamps are in original, uncancelled condition.
Series I (1937-1955) comprises albums formed during Mallender's early collecting years. The first three albums (volumes A-C) in this series form a general collection of Commonwealth stamps of the period. Organization is alphabetical, by country or territory. Stamps are placed in standard mounts, with multiple mounts affixed to the recto of each album page (on black paper). The majority of mounted items are individual stamps, with infrequent mounting of stamp sheets or booklets. The country or territory name is written in white ink at the top of each page, with additional notes interspersed describing the title or date of an individual stamp or series.
Volumes D and E of the first series house thematic collections. Volume D contains three themes: the 75th anniversary of the Universal Postal Union, in 1949; the Coronation of King George VI, 1937; and the Silver Wedding anniversary of George VI and Elizabeth Bowes-Lyon, 1948. Each of these three themes bears an original watercolor title page, in Mallender's youthful hand. Stamps within each theme are organized alphabetically by Commonwealth country or territory, without annotations. The next album (volume E) is also thematic, but the stamps are mounted on pages printed and organized by a publisher for each of the occasions. The first of these is titled British Empire Peace & Victory Issues published ca. 1946 by Royal Publishing House, Racine. The second is titled The White Ace Historical Album for the coronation of H.M. Queen Elizabeth II, published in 1953 by the Washington Press, Newark. In both parts, the publisher has allocated space for a fixed set of stamps to be collected, and Mallender has collected and mounted every stamp required.
Series II comprises the bulk of the collection, housed in 103 albums containing stamps produced between 1952 and 1988. This part of the collection is also organized alphabetically, by country or territory. Stamps are placed in standard mounts, with multiple mounts affixed to each album page (rectos only). The majority of items are individual stamps, but also mounted are numerous sheets or mini-sheets of stamps, as well as the occasional booklet of stamps. The country or territory name is written in ink at the top of each page, with additional notes in ink interspersed describing the title or date of a stamp series.
Series III comprises stamps produced in the British Commonwealth from 1988 to 1992. Stamps in this series are unmounted. Individual stamps, groups of stamps, sheets of stamps, or booklets of stamps have been placed by Mallender in wax paper envelopes of varying sizes. On each envelope, Mallender has written in black marker the prices paid for the stamps therein. The series is arranged alphabetically, by country or territory name.
Series IV comprises the 1999 edition of the Stanley Gibbons Stamp Catalogue: British Commonwealth, in two volumes. Throughout both volumes, ticks (check marks) have been placed next to the entries for select stamps. The ticks appear to be Mallender's record of stamps present within in his collection. The abundance of ticks indicates that Mallender collected a significant portion of Commonwealth stamps produced between 1937 and 1992.
Biographical / Historical
Fred Mallender graduated from Yale University in 1952 and received his doctorate from the University of Michigan Law School in 1955. He worked as an attorney in Bloomfield Hills, Michigan.
Postage stamps -- Commonwealth countries; Postage stamps -- Great Britain -- Colonies; Postage stamps -- Great Britain; Stamp collecting; Stamp collections; Stamp collectors; World War, 1939-1945 -- Peace -- On postage stamps; Commonwealth countries -- On postage stamps; Great Britain -- On postage stamps; Postage stamps; Stamp albums; Elizabeth, Queen of Great Britain, II, 1926- -- Coronation; Elizabeth, Queen of Great Britain, II, 1926- -- On postage stamps; Elizabeth, Queen, consort of George VI, King of Great Britain, 1900-2002 -- On postage stamps; George, King of Great Britain, VI, 1895-1952 -- Coronation; George, King of Great Britain, VI, 1895-1952 -- On postage stamps; Mallender, Fred, 1930-2003 -- Stamp collections; Universal Postal Union
- Early Albums, 1937-1955; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Comprises albums formed during Mallender's early collecting years. The first three albums (volumes A-C) in this series form a general collection of Commonwealth stamps of the period. Organization is alphabetical, by country or territory. Stamps are placed in standard mounts, with multiple mounts affixed to the recto of each album page (on black paper). The majority of mounted items are individual stamps, with infrequent mounting of stamp sheets or booklets. The country or territory name is written in white ink at the top of each page, with additional notes interspersed describing the title or date of an individual stamp or series.
  Volumes D and E of the first series house thematic collections. Volume D contains three themes: the 75th anniversary of the Universal Postal Union, in 1949; the Coronation of King George VI, 1937; and the Silver Wedding anniversary of George VI and Elizabeth Bowes-Lyon, 1948. Each of these three themes bears an original watercolor title page, in Mallender's youthful hand. Stamps within each theme are organized alphabetically by Commonwealth country or territory, without annotations. The next album (volume E) is also thematic, but the stamps are mounted on pages printed and organized by a publisher for each of the occasions. The first of these is titled British Empire Peace & Victory Issues published ca. 1946 by Royal Publishing House, Racine. The second is titled The White Ace Historical Album for the coronation of H.M. Queen Elizabeth II, published in 1953 by the Washington Press, Newark. In both parts, the publisher has allocated space for a fixed set of stamps to be collected, and Mallender has collected and mounted every stamp required.
  - General
    - Great Britain, and Aden-Canada (Box Vol. A)
      Includes:
      Great Britain, 1937-1951
      Great Britain, Offices in Africa, Middle East Forces, 1942-1947
      Great Britain, Offices in Africa, Eritrea, 1950-1951
      Great Britain, Offices in Africa, East Africa Forces, 1943-1946
      Great Britain, Offices in Africa, Somalia, 1948-1950
      Great Britain, Offices in Africa, Tripolitania, 1948-1951
      Morocco Agencies, 1937-1951
      Offices in Tangier, 1937-1951
      Aden, 1937-1951
      Aden, Kathiri State of Seiyun, 1942, 1951
      Aden, Qu'aiti State of Shihr and Mukalla, 1942, 1951
      Antigua, 1938-1948
      Ascension, 1938-1949
      Australia, 1937-1952
      Bahamas, 1938-1952
      Bahrain, 1938-1951
      Barbados, 1938-1952
      Basutoland, 1938
      Bechuanaland Protectorate, 1938
      Bermuda, 1938-1953
      British Guiana, 1938-1952
      British Honduras, 1938, 1949
      Brunei, 1947-1951
      Burma, 1945-1948
      Canada, 1937-1952
    - Cayman Islands-New Hebrides (Box Vol. B)
      Cayman Islands, 1938-1950
      Ceylon, 1938-1952
      Cook Islands, 1938-1952
      Cyprus, 1948-1944
      Dominica, 1938-1951
      Falkland Islands, 1938-1951
      Falkland Islands Dependencies, 1944-1948
      Fiji, 1938-1951
      Gambia, 1938-19546
      Gibraltar, 1938-1950
      Gilbert and Ellice Islands, 1938-1942
      Gold Coast, 1938-1948
      Grenada, 1937-1951
      Hong Kong, 1938-1947
      India (Dominion & Republic), 1937-1952
      Jamaica, 1938-1952
      Japanese Occupation, 1942-1943
      Kenya, Uganda & Tanganyika, 1938-1952
      Kuwait, 1939-1951
      Leeward Islands, 1938-1951
      Malaya Straits Settlements, 1945-1948
      Malaya, Johore, 1938-1952
      Malaya, Kedah, 1937-1952
      Malaya, Kelantan, 1937-1952
      Malaya, Malacca, 1950-1952
      Malaya, Negri Sembilan, 1949-1952
      Malaya, Pahang, 1950-1952
      Malaya, Penang, 1950-1952
      Malaya, Perak, 1938-1952
      Malaya, Perlis, 1951-1952
      Malaya, Singapore
      Malaya, Trengganu, 1941-1952
      Maldive Islands, 1951
      Malta, 1938-1943
      Mauritius, 1938-1950
      Montserrat, 1938-1951
      Muscat, 1944-1951
      Nauru, 1937-1947
      Newfoundland, 1938-1947
      New Guinea, 1938
      New Hebrides, 1938
    - New Zealand-Zanzibar (Box Vol. C)
      New Zealand, 1938-1953
      Nigeria, 1938-1951
      Niue (Cook Islands), 1938-1950
      Norfolk Island, 1947
      North Borneo, 1939-1950
      Northern Rhodesia, 1938-1952
      Nyasaland, 1930-1951
      Pakistan, 1947-1952
      Pakistan, Bahawalpur, 1945-1949
      Pitcairn Islands, 1940-1951
      St. Helena, 1938-1949
      St. Kitts Nevis, 1938-1952
      St. Lucia, 1938-1951
      St. Vincent, 1938-1952
      Samoa, 1939-1949
      Sarawak, 1946-1952
      Seychelles, 1938-1951
      Sierra Leone, 1938-1944
      Somaliland Protectorate, 1938-1951
      Southern Rhodesia, 1937-1955
      South-West Africa, 1937-1951
      Swaziland, 1938-1942
      Tokelau Islands, 1948
      Tonga, 1943-1951
      Trinidad & Tobago, 1938-1941
      Turks & Caicos Islands, 1938-1952
      Union of South Africa, 1937-1954
      Virgin Islands, 1938-1952
      Zanzibar, 1944
  - Thematic albums
    - Universal Postal Union, George VI Coronation, and 1948 Silver Wedding Anniversary (Box Vol. D)
    - British Empire Peace & Victory Issues, Queen Elizabeth II Coronation (Box Vol. E)
- Albums, 1947-1992; Series II
  Comprises the bulk of the collection, housed in 103 albums containing stamps produced between 1952 and 1988. This part of the collection is also organized alphabetically, by country or territory. Stamps are placed in standard mounts, with multiple mounts affixed to each album page (rectos only). The majority of items are individual stamps, but also mounted are numerous sheets or mini-sheets of stamps, as well as the occasional booklet of stamps. The country or territory name is written in ink at the top of each page, with additional notes in ink interspersed describing the title or date of a stamp series.
  - Abu Dhabi, 1964-1966 (Box Vol. 1)
    Also includes:
    Aden, 1953-1964
    Basutoland, 1952-1965
    Bechuanaland, 1954-1966
  - Aututaki, 1972-1982 (Box Vol. 2)
  - Aututaki, 1983-1987 (Box Vol. 3)
  - Australia, 1983-1986 (Box Vol. 4)
    Bermuda, 1953-1987
    Alderney, 1985-1987
  - Anguilla, 1967-1980 (Box Vol. 5)
  - Anguilla, 1981-1992? (Box Vol. 6)
    St. Lucia, 1986-1987
  - Antigua, 1952-1977 (Box Vol. 7)
  - Antigua, 1978-1981 (Box Vol. 8)
  - Antigua-Barbuda, 1981-1987? (Box Vol. 9)
  - Ascension, 1956-1987? (Box Vol. 10)
  - Australia, 1947-1983 (Box Vol. 11)
  - Bahamas, 1954-1987 (Box Vol. 12)
  - Bangladesh, 1971-1986 (Box Vol. 13)
    Belize, 1986-1987
  - Barbados, 1953-1987 (Box Vol. 14)
    Barbuda, 1985-1986
  - Barbuda, 1968-1979 (Box Vol. 15)
  - Belize, 1973-1986 (Box Vol. 16)
  - Botswana, 1966-1985 (Box Vol. 17)
  - British Honduras, 1953-1972 (Box Vol. 18)
    British West Indies, 1958
    Malaya, 1955-1965
  - British Antarctic Territory, 1963-1987 (Box Vol. 19)
    British Indian Ocean Territory, 1968-1986
  - Burma, 1954 (Box Vol. 20)
    Eire, 1953-1954
    Herm Island, 1952-1954
    Lundy, 1953-1954
    Nepal, 1953-1956?
    Trucial States, 1961
    Zanzibar, 1952-1967
  - Brunei, 1952-1987 (Box Vol. 21)
    Buddha Jayanti Burma/Ceylon, 1956
  - Caicos Islands, 1981-1985 (Box Vol. 22)
    Canada, 1976-1987
  - Canada, 1952-1977 (Box Vol. 23)
  - Cayman Islands, 1953-1987 (Box Vol. 24)
    Christmas Island, 1958-1987
  - Cocos Islands, 1963-1985? (Box Vol. 25)
    Cyprus, 1955-1987
  - Ceylon (Sri Lanka), 1953-1987 (Box Vol. 26)
  - Cook Islands, 1952-1975 (Box Vol. 27)
  - Cook Islands, 1975-1979 (Box Vol. 28)
  - Cook Islands, 1980-1983 (Box Vol. 29)
  - Cook Islands, 1984-1988 (Box Vol. 30)
  - Dominica, 1954-1977 (Box Vol. 31)
  - Dominica, 1977-1987 (Box Vol. 32)
  - East Africa (Kenya, Uganda, Tanzania), 1964-1974 (Box Vol. 33)
    Gilbert & Ellice Islands, 1956-1977
    St. Christopher / Nevis / Anguilla, 1954-1980
  - Falkland Islands, 1955-1987 (Box Vol. 34)
    Falkland Islands Dependencies, 1954-1985
  - Fiji, 1954-1987 (Box Vol. 35)
  - Gambia, 1953-1987 (Box Vol. 36)
  - Ghana, 1957-1971 (Box Vol. 37)
  - Ghana, 1972-1980 (Box Vol. 38)
  - Ghana, 1980-1987 (Box Vol. 39)
    Tokelau, 1956-1986
  - Gibraltar, 1953-1987 (Box Vol. 40)
  - Gilbert Islands, 1971-1978 (Box Vol. 41)
    New Hebrides, 1953-1980
  - Great Britain including officers & locals, 1952-1968 (Box Vol. 42)
  - Great Britain, 1968-1976 (Box Vol. 43)
  - Great Britain, 1976-1986 (Box Vol. 44)
  - Great Britain, 1984-1987 (Box Vol. 45)
  - Grenada, 1975-1978 (Box Vol. 46)
  - Grenada, 1978-1984 (Box Vol. 47)
  - Grenada, 1984-1987 (Box Vol. 48)
    Guyana, 1984-1986
  - Grenada (Grenadines), 1952-1974 (Box Vol. 49)
  - Grenada (Grenadines), 1975-1980 (Box Vol. 50)
  - Grenada (Grenadines), 1981-1987 (Box Vol. 51)
    St. Kitts, 1980-1987
  - Grenadines of St. Vincent, 1974-1987 (Box Vol. 52)
  - Guernsey, 1969-1987 (Box Vol. 53)
  - Guyana, 1966-1984 (Box Vol. 54)
  - Hong Kong, 1954-1987 (Box Vol. 55)
    Malawi, 1982-1986
  - India, 1953-1987 (Box Vol. 56)
  - Isle of Man, 1973-1987 (Box Vol. 57)
  - Jamaica, 1955-1987 (Box Vol. 58)
  - Jersey, 1969-1985 (Box Vol. 59)
  - Jersey, 1985-1987 (Box Vol. 60)
    Montserrat, 1985-1987
  - Kenya, 1963-1987 (Box Vol. 61)
  - Kiribati, 1979-1985 (Box Vol. 62)
    Norfolk Island, 1953-1986?
  - Lesotho, 1966-1987 (Box Vol. 63)
  - Malawi, 1964-1982 (Box Vol. 64)
  - Malaysia, 1952-1983 (Box Vol. 65)
  - Malaysia, 1983-1986 (Box Vol. 66)
    Malta, 1953-1987
  - Mauritius, 1953-1987 (Box Vol. 67)
  - Montserrat, 1952-1986 (Box Vol. 68)
  - Nauru, 1954-1987? (Box Vol. 69)
  - New Zealand, 1952-1979 (Box Vol. 70)
  - New Zealand, 1980-1986 (Box Vol. 71)
    Nigeria, 1953-1986
    Nigeria / Biafra, 1968-1969
  - Nevis, 1980-1992? (Box Vol. 72)
  - Niuafo'ou, 1983-1988 (Box Vol. 73)
    Tonga, 1984-1988
  - Niue, 1952-1982 (Box Vol. 74)
  - Niue, 1983-1987 (Box Vol. 75)
  - Pakistan, 1954-1987 (Box Vol. 76)
  - Papua New Guinea, 1952-1986 (Box Vol. 77)
    Penrhyn, 1982-1987
  - Penrhyn, 1973-1982 (Box Vol. 78)
  - Pitcairn Islands, 1957-1986 (Box Vol. 79)
    Redonda Antigua, 1979-1986
    Rhodesia, 1953-1978
    Ross Dependency, 1957-1979
    "Royal Visit," 1953-1954
    Sabah, 1964-1980?
    Bechuanoland, 1954-1966
  - Rhodesia & Nyasaland, 1954-1963 (Box Vol. 80)
    Somaliland Protectorate, 1953-1960
    South Africa, 1952-1961
    South Arabian Federation, 1963-1968
    South Rhodesia, 1953-1964
    Southwest Africa, 1952-1961
    Sudan, 1954
  - Samoa, 1952-1987 (Box Vol. 81)
  - St. Helena, 1953-1987 (Box Vol. 82)
    Sarawak, 1955-1986
    S. Georgia, 1963-1986
  - St. Lucia, 1953-1986 (Box Vol. 83)
  - St. Lucia, 1983-1985 (Box Vol. 84)
    Vanuatu, 1980-1987
  - St. Vincent, 1952-1980 (Box Vol. 85)
  - St. Vincent, 1980-1987 (Box Vol. 86)
  - Seychelles, 1954-1987 (Box Vol. 87)
  - Sierra Leone, 1952-1982 (Box Vol. 88)
  - Sierra Leone, 1981-1988 (Box Vol. 89)
  - Singapore, 1955-1986 (Box Vol. 90)
  - Solomon Islands, 1956-1987 (Box Vol. 91)
  - Swaziland, 1956-1987 (Box Vol. 92)
  - Tanganyika & Tanzania, 1961-1986 (Box Vol. 93)
  - Tonga, 1952-1975 (Box Vol. 94)
  - Tonga, 1976-1984 (Box Vol. 95)
  - Trinidad & Tobago, 1953-1986 (Box Vol. 96)
  - Tristan da Cunha, 1954-1987 (Box Vol. 97)
  - Turks and Caicos Islands, 1955-1981 (Box Vol. 98)
  - Turks and Caicos Islands, 1982-1987 (Box Vol. 99)
  - Tuvalu, 1976-1992? (Box Vol. 100)
  - Uganda, 1962-1986 (Box Vol. 101)
  - Virgin Islands, 1956-1987 (Box Vol. 102)
  - Zambia, 1964-1987 (Box Vol. 103)
    Zimbabwe, 1980-1986
- Later Stamps, Unmounted, 1988-1992; Series III
  Comprises stamps produced in the British Commonwealth from 1988 to 1992. Stamps in this series are unmounted. Individual stamps, groups of stamps, sheets of stamps, or booklets of stamps have been placed by Mallender in wax paper envelopes of varying sizes. On each envelope, Mallender has written in black marker the prices paid for the stamps therein. The series is arranged alphabetically, by country or territory name.
  - Aitutaki (Cook Islands) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anguilla (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Antigua & Barbuda (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Ascension (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Australia (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bahamas (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bangladesh (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Barbados (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Belize (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bermuda (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Botswana (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - British Antarctic Territory (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Brunei (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Canada (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Cayman Islands (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Christmas Islands (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cocos Islands (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Cook Islands (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Cyprus (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Dominica (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Falkland Islands (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Fiji (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The Gambia (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Ghana (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gibraltar (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Grenada (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Grenada (Grenadines) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Great Britain (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Guernsey (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Guyana (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Hong Kong (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - India (Box 3, Box 2)
  - Jamaica (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Jersey (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Kenya (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Kiribati (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Lesotho (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Malawi (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Malta (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Isle of Man (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Mauritius (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Montserrat (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Nevis (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - New Zealand (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Nigeria (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Niuafo'ou (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Niue (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Norfolk Island (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Pakistan (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Papua New Guinea (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Penrhyn (Northern Cook Islands) (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Pitcairn Islands (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Redonda (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Samoa (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Seychelles (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sierra Leone (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - Singapore (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - St. Helena (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - St. Kitts (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Saint Lucia (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - St. Vincent (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
  - Solomon Islands (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - South Georgia and South Sandwich Islands (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Sri Lanka (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Swaziland (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Tanzania (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Tonga (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Transkei (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Trinidad & Tobago (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Tristan da Cunha (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Turks & Caicos Islands (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Tuvalu (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Uganda (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Vanuatu (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - British Virgin Islands (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Zambia (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Zimbabwe (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Non-Commonwealth Countries (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - On Envelopes (Great Britain, etc.) (Box 5, Folder 13-14)
  - Registered letter envelopes (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Solomon Islands, 1987 America's Cup (Box 6)
    Consists of a large single sheet (24 x 31 cm) of Solomon Islands postage stamps commemorating the 1987 America's Cup.
- Gibbons Catalogues, 1999; Series IV
  Comprises the 1999 edition of the Stanley Gibbons Stamp Catalogue: British Commonwealth, in two volumes. Throughout both volumes, ticks (check marks) have been placed next to the entries for select stamps. The ticks appear to be Mallender's record of stamps present within in his collection. The abundance of ticks indicates that Mallender collected a significant portion of Commonwealth stamps produced between 1937 and 1992.
  - Vol. 1: Great Britain and countries A-I
  - Vol. 2: Countries J-Z